Finding Aid for Otis M. Smith Papers 1949-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Otis M. Smith Papers 1949-1993, 1957-1971
Smith, Otis Milton, 1922-1993.
3.5 linear feet
Attorney, Michigan state official, justice of the Michigan Supreme Court, 1961-1966, member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents, 1967-1971, general counsel and vice president of the General Motors Corporation. Series consist of Personal which includes biographical information and photographs; Speeches (1963-1992); Michigan Public Service Commission files (1957-1959); Auditor General files (1959-1961); General Motors Corporation files (1967-1969); University of Michigan Board of Regents files (1967-1971) which documents in part the Black Action Movement, the controversy over the role of R.O.T.C., and other issues involving the administration of the university; campaign files (1966-1968); and Michigan Supreme Court files (1961-1966).
9534 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This collection (Donor No. 8279 ) was donated by the Otis Smith estate in October, 1994.
The collection is open to research.
Otis M. Smith was born in Memphis, Tennessee, on February 20, 1922. He received his undergraduate education at Fisk University and Syracuse University. He received his law degree in 1950 from the Catholic University of America, Washington D.C. Over the course of his legal career he was admitted to practice in Michigan, the District of Columbia and the United States Supreme Court.
Otis M. Smith started his legal career as an assistant prosecutor in Flint, Michigan in 1950. He was appointed chairman of the Public Service Commission by Governor G. Mennen Williams in 1957. In 1959 Smith was appointed state auditor general of Michigan, a post to which he was subsequently elected in 1960. In 1961, he was named a justice of the Supreme Court of the State of Michigan, a post to which he was subsequently elected in 1962. Throughout his public service career, Smith was well known as one of the United States' highest ranking African-American elected or appointed officials.
Smith lost his bid for reelection to the State Supreme Court of the State of Michigan in 1966. In 1967 Smith accepted an appointment with the legal division of General Motors Corporation.
In 1967 Smith was named by Governor George Romney to the University of Michigan Board of Regents. Smith served out the remainder of Allen R. Sorenson's elected term but chose not to run for reelection in 1971. Smith's tenure as a university regent was laced with numerous incidences of campus unrest and disharmony within the university community.
Smith was named Associate General Counsel and Vice President of General Motors Corporation in 1974. He was elected to the post of General Counsel in 1977 by the GM Board of Directors, thus becoming one of the highest ranking African-Americans in corporate America. Smith retired from General Motors Corporation on 1 April, 1984 and went on to serve as counsel to the Detroit, Michigan law firm of Lewis, White and Clay.
Otis Smith died 29 June 1994 after a four year bout with prostate cancer at the age of 72.
The Otis M. Smith papers contains speeches, correspondence, examples of work produced in various offices, and photographs. This collection documents the career of a dedicated public servant and the many posts he held.
The Otis M. Smith papers are divided into eight series: Personal, Speeches, Michigan Public Service Commission Papers, Auditor General Papers, General Motors Papers, Regent Papers, Campaign Files and Supreme Court Papers.
Subjects:
Black Action Movement (University of Michigan); General Motors Corporation.; Michigan. Office of the Auditor General.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; Michigan. Public Service Commission.; Smith, Otis Milton, 1922-1994.; University of Michigan--Administration.; University of Michigan. Board of Regents.; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Douglas, William O. (William Orville), 1898-1980.; Judges--Michigan.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Marshall, Thurgood, 1908-1993.; Political elections.; Smith, Otis Milton, 1922-1994.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Personal 1949-1993
  Personal (4 folders; 1949-1993) includes biographical information and photographs of Otis M. Smith in a variety of poses and professional settings, as well as photos of contemporaries. The series also includes materials accumulated by Smith after his retirement from General Motors Corporation in 1984.
  - Biographical Information 1986 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Activities 1993 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    Portraits; photos of Smith with William O. Douglas and with John F. Kennedy; photo of G. Mennen Williams with Harry Truman, and of Thurgood Marshall and Wade McCree; also photos of Smith campaigning and with other judges and attorneys in various group settings.
    - 1949 (Box 1)
    - circa 1957-1961 (Box 1)
      (includes photo with John F. Kennedy)
    - circa 1962-1967 (Box 1)
    - circa 1962-1970 (Box 1)
    - circa 1963 (Box 1)
    - circa 1966 (Box 1)
    - undated (Box 1)
      (includes photo of G. Mennen Williams and Harry S. Truman and photo of Thurgood Marshall)
  - Publications 1979-1985 (Box 1)
- Speeches 1963-1992
  Speeches (.7 linear feet; 1963-1992) documents Otis M. Smith's career as a highly respected public servant, member of the legal community, and member of the corporate business world. A large percentage of the speeches are indexed and arranged in chronological order; the index can be found in the folder preceding the indexed speeches. Non-indexed speeches are also arranged chronologically and largely originate from the years following Smith's retirement from General Motors Corporation in 1984.
  - Indexed speeches
    - Index, undated December 1963-May 1983 (Box 1)
    - undated-December 1963 (Box 1)
    - 1964-June 1966 (Box 1)
    - May 1967-April 1968 (Box 1)
    - May 1968-December 1976 (Box 1)
    - September 1977-November 1978 (Box 1)
    - Spring 1979-October 1979 (Box 1)
    - January 1980-September 1980 (Box 1)
    - October 1980-September 1981 (Box 1)
    - January 1982-May 1983 (Box 1)
  - Non-indexed speeches
    - undated-February 1985 (Box 1)
    - February 17, 1985 (Box 1)
    - August 1985-April 1992 (Box 1)
  - Speech materials undated (Box 1)
- Michigan Public Service Commission Papers 1957-1959
  Michigan Public Service Commission Papers (4 folders; 1957-1959) documents Smith's tenure as chairman of the Michigan Public Service Commission. This series contains correspondence regarding Smith's appointment as chairman as well as correspondence originating from the office. This series also contains a press release authored by Smith detailing the commission and its functions. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - Appointment 1957 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - Press Release 1958 (Box 1)
- Auditor General Papers 1959-1961
  Auditor General Papers (7 folders; 1959-1961) documents the workings of the governmental position held by Smith prior to his appointment to the State Supreme Court of Michigan. This series contains correspondence and clippings relating the Auditor General's office. This series also contains examples of the office's work in the form of a survey conducted by Smith and samples of staff audit work. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - Auditor General Survey 1961 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Judicial Department 1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1959-1961 (Box 1)
  - Invitations 1961 (Box 1)
  - Staff Audit Work 1960-1961 (Box 1)
- General Motors Papers 1967-1969
  General Motors Papers (3 folders; 1967-1969) includes non-regent related materials originating from Smith's General Motors office. The majority of Smith's General Motors papers were removed prior to the donation of Smith's papers. The correspondence and other materials presented in this series document Smith's many roles outside his corporate job as a respected citizen and former member of the political realm. The folders are arranged alphabetically.
  - Flint Rate Manuals 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Personal 1967 (Box 1)
  - Personal 1968 (Box 1)
- Regent Papers 1967-1971
  Regent Papers (1.1 linear feet; 1967-1971) documents Smith's years as a member of the University of Michigan Board of Regents. Smith's regent papers cover a wide range of issues that serve to document the university when it was inundated with student unrest and the political climate of the United States in the late 1960s. Included in this series are folders on the following: Black Action Movement (B.A.M.), Reserve Officer Training Corps (R.O.T.C.), citizen dissatisfaction with the role of the regents and the role of the university president, The Michigan Daily, and admissions of students. The folders in this series are arranged alphabetically and often retain Smith's original folder headings. Some folders contain notes written by Smith regarding their content.
  - Administration 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - Admissions 1967-1971 (Box 1)
  - African-American Studies 1969 (Box 1)
  - Alumni 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Housing 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Association of Governing Boards of Universities and Colleges 1969 (Box 1)
  - Athletics 1967-1970 (Box 1)
  - Black Action Movement (B.A.M.)
    - Against 1970 (Box 1)
    - Demands 1970 (Box 1)
    - In Favor 1970 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Budget-Tuition 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Commission on Educational Reform 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Miscellaneous
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, Personal
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Other Colleges 1968 (Box 2)
  - Equal Opportunities Program 1968 (Box 2)
  - Faculty 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Flint College 1968 (Box 2)
  - Law School 1967 (Box 2)
  - Legal Matters 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Martin Luther King Memorial Scholarship Fund 1968-1970 (Box 2)
  - Medical Center 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Daily 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Union Study 1968 (Box 2)
  - Minority Groups 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Paul G. Goebel Endowed Chair Committee 1967 (Box 2)
  - Presidential Selection 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Rent Increase Letters 1970 (Box 2)
  - Reserve Officer Training Corps (R.O.T.C.) 1969-1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Rules, Sanctions and Disciplinary Procedures 1970 (Box 2)
  - Students 1967-1971 (Box 2)
  - University Hospital Committee 1967-1968 (Box 2)
  - University School Closure 1969 (Box 2)
  - Urban-Related Programs 1968 (Box 2)
- Campaign Files 1962-1968
  Campaign Files (.5 linear feet; 1966-1968) documents various political campaigns in the state of Michigan, notably Smith's 1962 successful and 1966 unsuccessful re-election campaigns for the State Supreme Court of Michigan. This series also documents Smith's involvement in Hubert Humphrey's 1968 Presidential bid. The folders are arranged chronologically.
  - 1958 Michigan Campaigns, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - 1962 Campaign
    - Ballot Proofs 1962 (Box 3)
    - Clippings 1962 (Box 3)
    - Congratulations 1962 (Box 3)
    - Contributions 1962 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1962 (Box 3)
    - Friends for Otis Smith 1962 (Box 3)
    - Invitations 1962 (Box 3)
    - Paul Adams 1962 (Box 3)
    - Press Releases 1962 (Box 3)
    - Schedules 1962 (Box 3)
  - 1966 Campaign
    - Campaign Biographies 1966 (Box 3)
    - Campaigning Materials 1966 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1966 (Box 3)
    - Expenses 1966 (Box 3)
    - Invitations/Endorsements 1966 (Box 3)
    - Offers of Aid 1966 (Box 3)
    - Press Releases 1966 (Box 3)
    - Schedules 1966 (Box 3)
    - Secretary's File 1966 (Box 3)
  - Post-1966 Judgeship Bid 1966 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Party Materials 1967 (Box 3)
  - Democratic Party Materials 1968 (Box 3)
  - Humphrey (Hubert) Campaign 1968 (Box 3)
- Supreme Court Papers 1961-1990
  Supreme Court Papers (1 linear foot; 1961-1990) documents Smith's tenure as a justice of the State Supreme Court of Michigan. Included are opinions/window matters authored by Smith on cases presented to the court, a folder of opinions Smith deemed his "best cases," court memorandums authored by Smith, folders on specific court matters, and a survey conducted by the court. The folders in this series are arranged alphabetically and are closed to researchers until the death of all of the members of the court who served with Smith.
  - Agendas 1961-1966 (Box 4)
  - Appointment 1961 (Box 4)
  - Audiotape of Otis M. Smith sponsored by Michigan Supreme Court Historical Society 1990 (Box 4)
  - "Best Cases," 1965-1966 (Box 4)
  - Case Review 1961-1966 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Administrative Law 1966 (Box 4)
  - Court Employee Records 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Intermediate Courts of Appeal 1963 (Box 4)
  - Judge Doran Matter 1961 (Box 4)
  - Memorandums 1962-1966 (Box 4)
  - Minor Courts 1965 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous and Annotated Documents 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Opinions (Index) circa 1967 (Box 4)
  - Opinions/Window Matters
    - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
    - 1962-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1964, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Pretrial Rule Amendments 1966 (Box 4)
  - Reapportionment Matters 1964 (Box 4)
  - Rule Changes 1963-1966 (Box 4)
  - Statistical Break-Downs 1966, undated (Box 4)
  - Survey of Michigan Supervisors by County 1965 (Box 4)
  - Window Matter Conference Sheets
    - 1961-1964, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1965 (Box 4)
    - 1966, 3 folders (Box 4)